It is the turbulent Sengoku period.
어지러운 전국 시대.
Warlords keep on fighting day and night over Jipangu State, where Karakuri people live.
카라쿠리인이 사는 지팡구국에서는 군웅할거하여 밤낮으로 접전이 계속되고
Karakuri martial artists were sharpening their swords, dreaming of victory and honor.
카라쿠리 무예가들도 승리와 영광을 꿈꾸며 맹렬히 싸우고 있었다.
And now, a wild hero has arrived, seeking to be the number one Karakuri martial artist!
그리고 지금, 카라쿠리 무예가 제일을 꿈꾸는 터무니없는 영웅이 탄생했다!
Musashi is here-dasu!
무사시 등장이오!
Karakuri Kengouden
카라쿠리 검호전: 무사시 로드
A man always dreams of the day
사내는 언제나 세계 한가운데서
in the center of the world to become
제일 강해질 날을
AH! AH! the strongest
아! 아! 꿈꿔라
Raise the sword of your heart high to the wide sky
마음의 칼을 넓은 하늘로 번쩍 쳐들어
Raise the curtain to the road of adventure
모험의 길의 막을 연다
A skilled swordsman roams on Jipangu State
지팡구국을 떠도는 검호
His name is Musashi, a Karakuri man
그 이름은 카라쿠리인 무사시
Go! Fight!
가라! 싸워라!
The sound of fierce duels
격렬한 승부의 소리는
makes life dazzling
눈부신 인생
Battles of yesterdays make you stronger today
싸웠던 어제보다도 오늘 강해진다
Martial Arts! Dual Blade Musashi
무예! 이도류 무사시
Tomorrow will be glorious
내일은 빛난다
The sound of fierce duels
격렬한 승부의 소리는
makes life dazzling
눈부신 인생
Fight the utmost with the stillness
싸우는 한껏 고요함과 함께
Martial Arts! Dual Blade Musashi
무예! 이도류 무사시
His eyes shined! Musashi!
미간이 반짝였다 무사시!!
The Karakuri people are a race of superhuman beings living in Jipangu State.
카라쿠리인이라는 것은 지팡구국에 사는 슈퍼 인류이다.
They hone their martial skills all day and night, giving it all they got to fight for victory and honor.
밤낮으로 무예를 갈고 닦으며 힘을 기르며 승리와 영광을 위해 전력으로 싸운다.
They will be rewarded with fame, if not death.
그 보수는 명예인가 죽음인가.
In this unstable Jipangu state, spirits of love and friendship burst.
이 뜬구름과 같은 지팡구국에 사랑과 우정의 혼이 작렬한다.
To the Road of Adventure-dasu!
대모험의 길로 떠나오!
The turbulence of Sengoku period notwithstanding, Miyamoto village was a peaceful place on hilly region at Chūgoku.
전국 시대는 어지러운 시기였지만, 이곳 주고쿠 산지의 미야모토 마을은 평화로운 곳이었다.
Hey! Stop! Egg thief!
이녀석! 멈춰라! 계란 도둑이다!
I'm not a thief-dasu! I asked the chickens to give me some eggs-dasu!
도둑 아니오! 저는 알을 가져다 달라고 닭씨에게 부탁했소!
You asked the chickens, you say!?
닭한테 부탁했다고!?
Right-dasu! This is proof!
응이오! 잘 모르겠다면!
Cuckoo!
꼬끼오!
Are you making fun of me? Unforgivable!
날 놀려먹을 셈이냐! 용서할 수 없다!
Musashi
무사시
I'm not making fun of you-dasu. When I become the number one martial artist of Jipangu State,
놀려먹는 것 아니오. 내가 지팡구 제일의 무예가가 된다면
I'll repay you by tenfold, no, by hundredfold-dasu!
열 배, 아니, 백 배로 돌려주겠소이다!
What kind of number one martial artist will you be with that wide open mouth!?
뭐가 제일의 무예가냐? 이 허풍쟁이야!
My legs have given out...
더 이상 못 달려...
May I be visited by many customers today...
오늘도 손님이 많이 오도록...
As if it'd be raining with customers!
정말 많이 오도록!
Thanks!
가져가겠소!
Hey! Musashi, you wretch!
야! 무사시 망나니 녀석이!
-Looks tasty! -Awesome!
-맛있어 보여! -대단해!
You need power and stamina to become the number one martial artist of Jipangu-dasu!
지팡구 제일의 무예가가 되기 위해선 먼저 스태미나와 파워이오!
Here, eat up-dasu!
자, 모두 먹으시오!
Thank you!
네!
Alright! Since we're done eating, it's time to train-dasu!
좋소, 잘 먹었다면 무예 단련의 시간이오!
I lost!
졌다!
Good! I'll face you this time!
좋소, 다음은 제가 상대이오!
Attack me whenever you're ready-dasu!
자, 어디서든 덤벼 보시오!
It hurts!
아프잖아!
Fighting you one by one will take forever, so attack me all at once-dasu!
에이, 성가시게! 모두 한번에 덤벼들어 보시오!
Back then, Musashi was 11 years old. He was the leader among the kids of Miyamoto village.
그 때, 무사시, 열한 살. 미야모토 마을의 골목대장이었다.
I'm still standing! Come at me!
아직아직아직! 자, 덤벼들어 보시오!
We're done!
괜찮아!
Is there anyone here who isn't a coward-dasu?
뭐야, 겁쟁이뿐이오...
That's not it! It's just that you're too strong!
그런 거 아니야! 무사시 형이 강한 거야!
Hearing that has given me strength-dasu.
그런 소리를 듣다니 제가 더욱 강해진 기분이 드는 것 같소.
He got the strength of beasts.
정말 뚝심이야...
And he's a glutton, too.
게다가 완전 밥보야.
Huh? Did you say something-dasu?
어? 뭐라 하셨소?
Nope, not a thing!
아, 아무 소리도 안 했습니다!
I don't believe you. You shall not trick the ears of a martial artist-dasu.
아니오. 무예가의 귀를 간지럽히면 곤란하오.
I definitely heard you calling me names-dasu.
분명히 뚝심에 밥보라고 말했소.
Musashi's angry! Run for it!
무사시 형 화났다! 도망쳐!
Damn you! It's cowardly to run away-dasu!
네이놈! 달아나다니 비겁하오!
That must be the scream of lovely Otsuru!
이건 사랑스러운 오츠루 씨의 비명!
Otsuru! Otsuru!
오츠루 씨! 오츠루 씨!
Please help, anyone!
아무나 살려주세요!
Musashi was devoted to this beautiful girl named Otsuru.
이 미소녀야말로 무사시가 온 사랑을 바친 오츠루였다.
Back then, Otsuru was 9 years old.
그 때 오츠루, 9살.
Stop! Halt!
멈춰! 멈추시오!
Musashi is here-dasu!
무사시 등장이오!
Otsuru, are you hurt-dasu?
오츠루 씨, 상처는 괜찮소?
Nope! Musashi, thank you!
네, 무사시 씨! 고마워요!
Don't mention it. A martial artist must rescue girls in trouble-dasu!
별 말씀을! 연약한 소녀를 구하는 것은 무예가의 일이오!
You're so strong, Musashi.
무사시 씨 강하네요.
You think so-dasu?
그, 그런 정도이오?
I like strong people.
강한 사람이 좋아!
I'm happy to hear that-dasu!
좋다니 그런 말씀을 해 주시다니 기쁘오!
Musashi!
무사시 씨!
I like it when you say Musashi-dasu, Otsuru!
아니, 무사시라고 불러 주오, 오츠루 씨!
Oh, please!
이야, 부끄럽게!
What are you talking about? Behind you!
뭔 소리에요, 뒤! 뒤!
What is it-dasu?
뭐오?
Were you still alive-dasu?
이 녀석, 아직 살아 있었소?
Don't do it, Musashi.
하지 마요, 무사시 씨.
To show your back to an enemy is shameful-dasu! Leave this to me and get away-dasu!
적에게 등을 보이는 것은 무예가의 수치오! 여기는 제게 맡기고 달아나시오!
Now, let's have a fair match-dasu!
자, 일대일 승부를 보자!
How insolent!
이런 버릇없는!
Musashi!
무사시 씨!
Hey! Stop!
멈추시오!
Hey! Stop-dasu! You damn thing!
멈추시오! 이 놈!
Hey! What are you doing!?
야! 뭔 짓이냐!
I actually don't like washing~
사실은 세탁 싫어~
Stop running!
멈춰라!
Huh?
어?
Miss, get out of the way-dasu!
아주머니, 위험하오!
What on earth!?
오면 어쩌냐!
Musashi, what are you doing, you good-for-nothing!
무사시, 뭔 짓이냐, 이 쓸모없는 놈아!
Hey, when are you going to stop-dasu? Stop right now-dasu!
어이, 언제까지 계속 달릴 생각이냐! 곧장 멈춰라!
What's going on?
어? 대체 뭔 일이래?
Watch out-dasu! Everyone move!
위험하오! 모두 비키시오!
Kojirō
코지로
Watch out-dasu!
위험하오!
Move or you'll get hurt-dasu!
비키시오! 다치오!
This was the fated encounter between Musashi and Kojirō.
이것이 무사시와 코지로의 운명의 만남이었다.
Back then, Kojirō was 13 years old.
그 때, 코지로, 13살.
You shouldn't act so carelessly. Be careful, kiddo.
까불면 다친다. 조심해라, 꼬마야.
Kiddo? I won't forgive anyone who insults me-dasu! If you're a martial artist, then I challenge you-dasu!
꼬마라고? 날 모욕하는 건 참을 수 없소! 무예가라면 승부를 보시오!
Hey! Stop! If you don't stop, I'll chase you-dasu!
거기, 멈추시오! 안 멈추면 뒤쫓겠소!
Stop it, Musashi!
그만 못할까, 무사시!
I can't forgive someone so pretentious like that-dasu! Don't get in my way-dasu!
저 저런 아니꼬운 용서할 수 없소! 승부를 방해하지 마시오!
Silence!
어디서 말대꾸!
You hit me! Even if you're the master Takuan, I won't forgive you-dasu!
이런! 아무리 타쿠안 스님이라도 용서할 수 없소!
-He's over there! -He'll face my wrath today!
-무사시가 있다! -오늘로 본때를!
Musashi! Unforgivable!
무사시! 용서할 수 없다!
Ouch! It hurts-dasu! That's cowardly-dasu!
아야야! 아프오! 비겁하오!
-You should be begging to be forgiven! -It serves you right! -Musashi did it again!
-용서를 빌지 못할 망정! -싸다, 싸! -무사시 놈!
Stop it! You've done enough!
그만두세요! 이제 그만해요!
Otsuru, somebody so violent shouldn't be let off the hook!
오츠루, 이런 난폭한 사람은 맞아도 싸!
That's right, my chicken cage is broken thanks to him! I won't forgive him!
그래, 이 녀석 때문에 닭장이 부서졌던 참이다! 오늘 절대 용서 못 해!
Let's tie him up and throw him into a river!
자! 대발로 감아 강에 쳐넣자!
Sure, then! Set me on fire or boil me; do whatever you want-dasu!
알았소! 빨랑빨랑 태우든 삶든 마음대로 하시오!
Okay, then. We'll do as you wish.
좋아, 원하는 대로 해 주겠어!
Forgive him! Please!
용서해 주세요! 부탁드립니다!
It's true that Musashi is violent. But he pounced on a raging cow and saved me!
분명히 무사시는 난폭해요. 그래도 날뛰는 소 앞에 뛰어들어서 절 구해 주었어요!
He is greatly courageous! So don't kill him! Please!
대단한 용기를 가졌어요! 그러니까 생명은 살려 주세요! 부탁드립니다!
Otsuru...
오츠루 씨...
If you say so...
그렇게 말하면...
What should we do?
어떻게 할까요, 여러분?
Takuan
타쿠안
Leave this to me for now.
여기는 일단 제게 맡겨 보시지요.
Master.
스님.
You deceived me! Takuan, you stupid old monk! A liar! Dusty butt! A witch!
잘도 속였겠다! 타쿠안 마법 땡중 거짓말쟁이 얼간이!
Musashi! Take in the breadth of the world and cool down!
무사시! 천하의 넓음을 보고 머리를 식혀라!
I hate self-reflection as much as Takuan-dasu! I'll show you-dasu!
반성하고 타쿠안 제일 싫소! 두고 보시오!
Will he end up being a crow's food, hanging on a tree!? Wait for the stormy latter half!
나무에 매달려 까마귀 먹이가 되고 마는가! 질풍노도의 후반을 기다려라!
That stupid unworthy so-called martial artist, using a sword longer than himself!
저 아니꼬운 무예가 놈, 키보다도 긴 칼이나 만지는 주제에!
Some day, I'll become the best and make him a laughingstock-dasu!
언젠가는 내가 제일이 되어 웃음거리로 삼아 주겠소!
I'm hungry-dasu...
배고프오...
Hey! Fishy smelling! Stupid monk! Shorty! Liar! Let me go-dasu!
야! 비린내나는 마법 땡중 거짓말쟁이 땅딸막이! 날 놓으시오!
Have you done some reflection?
조금은 반성했나!
Never, even if I have to die-dasu!
반성은 죽어도 안 하오!
Oh? I praise your determination and determination alone.
오? 그 근성만은 칭찬해 주지.
Of course-dasu! I will become the best martial artist of Jipangu...
당연하오! 난 지팡구 제일의 무예가로...
The world is broad! You are even more ignorant of the ways of the world than those frogs in the well,
세상은 넓다! 너 따위는 저 우물 안 개구리보다도 세상에 물정에 어두운 주제에 힘 자랑이고 실력 자랑이고 하는 게 구리터분하다!
What a nice manju!
만주 한번 맛있구나!
Manju...
만주!
Close your mouth! Shut up-dasu!
시끄러워! 닥치시오!
Will I ever reflect? No way! Never-dasu!
반성따위 할까보냐! 절대 안 하오!
Musashi! Musashi!
무사시 씨! 무사시 씨!
O- Otsuru!
오, 오츠루 씨!
Musashi, are you all right?
무사시 씨, 괜찮아요?
Yes, this is nothing-dasu!
이 정도는 괜찮소!
Please, don't be so stubborn. Ask for forgiveness!
저, 부탁이에요, 고집부리지 마세요. 스님하고 모두에게 사과하세요!
I didn't do anything wrong-dasu!
난 사과해야 하는 일은 안 했소!
Musashi!
무사시 씨!
To become the number one martial artist of Jipangu, I will never break down, no matter what-dasu!
지팡구 제일의 무예가가 되기 위해선 어떤 아픈 일에도 꺾이지 않소!
That's what it means to be a man-dasu!
그것이 사내라는 것이오!
I made a rice ball for you.
주먹밥 만들어 왔어요.
Rice ball? Otsuru! I'm so happy-dasu!
주먹밥? 오츠루 상! 기쁘오!
Quick! Throw it up here-dasu!
빨리! 여기로 던져올려 주세요!
Here goes!
이랴!
Master!
스님!
I'll be handing this rice ball over to the Buddha.
이 주먹밥은 부처님께 가져다 드리겠다.
Master...
스님...
Hey! Otsuru made that rice ball just for me-dasu!
야! 그 주먹밥은 오츠루 씨가 절 위해 만들어 준 것이라오!
You are not qualified to eat a rice ball made with such kindness!
네게 상냥함이 담긴 이 주먹밥을 먹을 자격은 없다!
Damn you! Thief! Give my rice ball back!
젠장! 도둑! 주먹밥 돌려줘!
-That's mine! -He's not reflecting at all.
-내 것이오! -전혀 반성하질 않는구나.
-Give it back right now! -Otsuru, you should go home or you'll catch a cold.
-당장 돌려주시오! -자, 오츠루 씨도 돌아가세요. 감기 걸려요.
-Cursed Takuan! My rice ball! -Musashi!
-타쿠안 땡중할배! 내 주먹밥! -무사시 씨!
Idiot! dasu!
나쁜 놈! 이오!
I feel sorry for Musashi.
무사시 형님 불쌍해...
What are you talking about? He did something bad and got what was coming to him. You guys should learn from this.
무슨. 당해도 싸다. 알았어? 나쁜 짓을 한 벌이다. 너희들도 보고 깨달아라.
Even the sparrows...
참새 놈들까지 날...
Idiot!
멍청아!
Damn you! Idiot!
젠장! 멍청이!
Dear god, Musashi is violent. But he would never bully the weak!
신이시여, 무사시는 난폭합니다. 그래도 약한 자를 괴롭히진 않아요.
Please help him.
어떻게든 도와 주세요.
I won't do anything-dasu. So please, come here-dasu.
나 아무것도 안 할 테니까 여기로 와주시오!
It's lonely up here alone-dasu...
혼자서는 외롭소....
Come on, just a little bit more! Take a rest on me-dasu!
오, 좀만 더! 제게 앉으시오!
Not yet.
아직이구나.
Musashi was hung on a tree. Another day passed, and Takuan still did not forgive him.
나무에 매달린 무사시. 타쿠안의 용서를 받지 않고 계속 날날이 지난다.
-He's still there... -He might collapse if he doesn't get down.
-아직도 매달려 있다니... -이대로라면 뻗을지도 모르겠네.
But the master hasn't forgiven him yet.
그래도 이 스님 아직도 용서치 않겠다고 하시니 원...
He's a brat, but then he's just a kid.
악동이어도 아이는 아이잖아.
I won't do anything to you-dasu. So please, come to me-dasu.
나 아무것도 안 하오. 그러니까 와 주오.
Please-dasu... I'm so lonely here alone-dasu.
부탁이오... 혼자서는 외롭소.
Master!
스님!
Look at that.
저걸 봐라.
The sparrows!
참새가 저렇게나!
Abandoning the thoughts to become stronger or to take enemies down, he indeed became selfless.
강해지겠다거니 상대를 쓰러뜨리겠다거니 하는 생각을 버리고 무사를 달성했으니 말이다.
-Selfless? -A pure and beautiful spirit has given him sparrow friends.
-무사? -순수하고 아름다운 마음. 그게 참새를 친구로 부른 게다.
Look! Master!
어라? 스님!
It's fine. Act like you didn't see a thing.
괜찮아. 모르는 척 해.
Musashi!
무사시 씨!
Otsuru!
오츠루 씨!
I'm going to save you!
지금 구해 드릴게요.
It's all right now!
이제 괜찮네요!
But Otsuru, you're going to be scolded-dasu!
그래도 오츠루 씨 혼나겠소!
No, don't worry about it. I was happy to see you with those sparrows!
아니에요, 걱정하지 말고 전 무사시 씨가 참새하고 같이 있는 걸 보고 정말 기뻤어요!
You really have a kind spirit inside of you!
그러니까 무사시 씨 사실은 정말 마음이 착한 걸 알겠어요!
You're making me blush-dasu...
수줍소...
Musashi?
무사시 씨?
What is it?
뭐오?
I made some rice balls for you.
이거 주먹밥이에요.
Otsuru!
오츠루 씨!
I hope that Master will understand.
스님도 알아주실 거에요.
Agreed.
그러오.
Musashi ran away!
무사시가 도망쳤다!
Quick!
빨리!
Follow your dreams.
꼭 꿈을 이루세요!
Thank you. I will definitely become the number one martial artist of Jipangu-dasu!
고맙소. 난 꼭 지팡구 제일의 무예가가 되겠소!
Otsuru, I... I...
오츠루 씨, 저... 저...
Yes, what is it?
네, 뭐에요?
I... I'd like a farewell from you-dasu!
저... 작별인사를 해 주면 고맙겠소!
Stay well, Musashi!
건강하세요, 무사시 씨!
Musashi!
무사시 씨!
When I manage to become the number one martial artist, I will marry Otsuru-dasu!
나, 최강의 무예가가 된다면 꼭 오츠루 씨를 부인으로 맞이하겠소!
Please wait until then-dasu!
그 때까지 기다려 주시오!
Otsuru's rice balls taste so good-dasu!
오츠루 씨가 만들어 준 주먹밥 정말 맛있소!
He's from back then...
그 때 그...
Wait a moment-dasu!
잠, 잠깐 기다리시오!
Are you talking to me?
기다리라는 건 나 말인가.
That's right-dasu. For my training, I'd like you to be my opponent-dasu.
그, 그렇소. 나, 무예의 수련을 위해 상대가 되어 주길 부탁드리오.
You have rice stuck to your face.
얼굴에 밥풀이나 붙이고 다니는 주제에 무슨 소리를.
Aren't you that kiddo from a few days ago?
너, 아까 그 꼬마 아니냐.
I'm not a kiddo-dasu! I am Musashi from Miyamoto village-dasu!
꼬마 아니오! 난 미야모토 마을의 무사시이오!
I'll cut it short. You should go back and help with fieldworks.
나쁜 소리는 하지 않겠다. 마을에 돌아가서 밭일이나 도와줘라.
Damn you, don't look down on me-dasu!
네이놈, 업신여기지 마시오!
Face me!
승부!
It's cowardly to jump up-dasu!
뛰어 올라가다니 비겁하오!
And attacking from behind isn't?
뒤에서 달려드는 것은 비겁한 것이 아니냐!
That doesn't matter-dasu!
그건 아무래도 상관없소!
What a dimwit.
머리 안 돌아가는 녀석이군.
But calling me, Mister Kojirō, a coward would be a dishonor to my name!
어쨌든 비겁하다고 불리기에는 이 미스터 코지로의 이름이 깎이는구나!
So your name is Kojirō-dasu?
네 녀석은 코지로라고 하는 놈이오?
How shall I call someone who doesn't know of me, the famous Kojirō? An ignorant? A moron?
무예에 뜻이 흐르는 코지로를 모른다는 것은 무지라 할지 천치라 할지!
How astonishing!
기막힌 놈이구나!
Fine-dasu! If you're a famous martial artist, then I will take you down and make myself famous-dasu!
좋소! 이름 있는 무예가라면 내가 쓰러뜨려 이름을 세우겠소!
Sure! I'll show you how relentless is the path of martial arts!
좋다! 무예의 길이란 얼마나 혹독한 것인지 알려 주겠다!
Here I come!
무사시 등장!
Secret Sword Tsubamegaeshi!
비검! 츠바메가에시!
(Tsubamegaeshi: 燕返し. lit. Swallow Reversal)
(츠바메가에시: 燕返し. 말 그대로는 제비 뒤집기)
Farewell, Musashi. Idiot.
안녕이다, 무사시. 바보 녀석.
Hey! The match isn't...
야! 승부는 아직...
No way...
말도 안 돼...
I'm so embarrassed-dasu...
나... 나, 분하오...
Musashi, cheer up!
무사시 씨, 힘내요!
Otsuru...
오츠루 씨...
Musashi stood up and started to walk. But the road towards discipline is tough.
무사시는 일어섰다. 그리고 걷기 시작했다. 그러나 수련의 길은 험한 것이다.
What kind of harsh fate will be waiting for him? Whatever it is, never give up, Musashi! Keep walking and become a man.
앞으로 어떠한 가혹한 운명이 기다리는가. 그러나 꺾이지 마라, 무사시! 앞으로 나아가라! 그것이 사내의 길이다.
You wait and see, Kojirō!
두고 보시오, 코지로여!
Sometimes the moon jumps over
허공의 주머니에 달이
the pocket of empty sky
뛰어넘어가는 일도 있어
Laugh loudly and
큰 소리로 웃으면
morning will come tomorrow
내일에는 아침이 와
Don't worry too much about losing
잃는 것 따위는 아무것도 아니야
Keep going! Go for it!
계속 해나가! 앞으로 가!
A bare hand is strong
맨손은 강해
That's how it is! Let's go lightly
그런 거야! 가볍게 가자
That's how life is! Look, a chance
인생 그런 거야! 기회가 어라,
follows us wagging its tail!
꼬리를 흔들며 쫒아와!
That's how it is! Let's go lightly
그런 거야! 가볍게 가자
That's how the future is, too! Look, tomorrow
미래도 그런 거야! 내일이 어라,
is opening its hands and smiling at us!
양손을 벌리고 웃고 있어!
To think that there's someone stronger than me, wow! The world is broad-dasu!
나보다 강한 놈이 있다니, 이야, 세계는 넓소!
Things get messed up and I fight against Yoshioka clan,
일이 꼬여 요시오카 일족과 척을 지게 되었지만,
but Master Bokuden appeared like a wind and saved me.
그 순간, 바람과도 같이 나타난 보쿠덴 선생님.
I followed him and managed to become his student-dasu.
난 바로 쫒아가서 제자가 되었소.
Next episode: Training in Tears Makes Me Hungry-dasu.
다음 이야기! 눈물의 수행은 배가 고프오
Don't miss it-dasu!
꼭 봐야 하오!
Next Episode
다음 이야기
Training In Tears
눈물의 수행은 배가 고프오
Makes Me Hungry
기대하세요!